Temple, Thomas, 1614-1674. Thomas Temple correspondence concerning Nova Scotia, 1656-1768 (MS Am 1249): Guide.
Thomas Temple correspondence concerning Nova Scotia,
1656-1768.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Am 1249
Temple, Thomas, 1614-1674.
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Contains chiefly correspondence of British proprietor and governor of Nova Scotia Thomas Temple and his nephew John Nelson concerning land claims in Nova Scotia and the French role in Canada
51M-224. Gift of Mrs. G. L. Batchelder, Jr., Moraine Farm Beverly, Massachusetts, Mr. Gordon Abbott, and Mrs. Francis B. Lothrop; received: 1951.
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material. Collection is open for research.
Thomas Temple (1614-1674) was a British proprietor and governor of Nova Scotia; John Nelson (1654-1734) was a New England trader and statesman.
Contains chiefly correspondence of Thomas Temple and his nephew John Nelson concerning land claims in Nova Scotia and the French role in Canada. Temple's correspondence includes letters from several 17th-century British sovereigns; Nelson's correspondence also pertains to negotiations for his release from prison in France. Includes some correspondence of Paschal Nelson and a few Nelson family records.
- Saye and Sele, William Fiennes, 1st viscount, 1582-1662. A.L.s. to Sir Thomas Temple; [London] 9 Feb 1656., (1); 1s.(2p.)
  Offers a horse for sale to Temple's brother for £60.
- Gt. Brit. Sovereigns, etc., 1649-1658; (Oliver Cromwell) Grant of Lacadie part of Nova Scotia to Sir Charles St. Stephen,; Thomas Temple; Wm. Crown. MS.(notarial copy made ca.1750); London, 10 Jul and 8 Sep 1656., (2); 3s.(8p.)
- [Temple, Sir William, bart., 1614-1674] A breviate of ye purchase of Nova Scotia. MS.(unsigned); [London? ca.1656], (3); 1s.(1p.);
  with this is Transcript made ca. 1750.
- Manchester, Edward Montagu, 2nd earl of, 1602-1671. MS.s.; [London] 26 Feb 1661/1662., (4); 1s.(1p.)
  Certificate of Sir Thomas Temple's appointment as gentleman in ordinary of his majesty's privy chamber.
- Gt. Brit. Sovereigns, etc., 1660-1685. (Charles II) MS.s.(Edw. Nicholas); Hampton Court, 7 Jul 1662., (5); 1s.(1p.)
  Official direction from the Attorney General to prepare a bill creating Col. Thomas Temple Baronet of Nova Scotia.
- Russell, Thomas. An accompt of disbursments, laid out for the building of a fort at Port Rosignall... MS.s.; [n.p.] 1664., (6); 1s.(1p.)
  A detailed account of expenses, plus explanation of why fort was financial failure.
- Massachusetts (colony). General Court. Att a Generall Court held at Boston in New England... MS.s.(Edward Rawson); Boston, 10 Oct 1666., (7); 1s.(1p.)
  Official recognition of Sir Thomas Temple's jurisdiction in Nova Scotia.
- Temple, Sir Thomas, bart., 1614-1674. A.L.s. to John Nelson; Boston, 9 Oct 1667., (8); 1s.(1p.)
  A letter mainly of spiritual and moral advice.
- Gt. Brit. Treaties, etc., 1660-1685. (Charles II) Breda. 10th 11th article for del'up Lacadie. MS.s.(Arlington); [n.p.,1667], (9); 1s.(2p.)
  These articles provide for the restoration of Acadia to France. Arlington was Secretary of State.
- Gt. Brit. Sovereigns, etc., 1660-1685. (Charles II) MS.(unsigned, contemporary copy); Whitehall, 6 Aug 1669., (10); 1s.(2p.)
  Final order for the surrender of Nova Scotia to the French in accordance with the Treaty of Breda.
- Temple, Sir Thomas, bart., 1614-1674. My comision from my uncle Sr. Tho. Temple. MS.s.; [n.p.] 17 Mar 1669/1670., (11); 1s.(1p.)
  The commission of John Nelson as Deputy Governor of Nova Scotia.
- Denton, William, 1605-1691. A.L.s. to Sir Thomas Temple; [London] 27 Feb 1670/1671., (12); 1s.(2p.)
  Request for Temple to return a £25 "venture" which had been placed with him by a cousin; brief summary of news, of the court.
- Temple, Stephen. A.L.s. to [Sir Thomas Temple]; [London] 20 Sep 1671., (13); 1s.(2p.)
  Letter of introduction carried by Stephen's younger brother, who was going to America to seek his fortune.
- Dongan, Thomas, 2nd earl of Limerick, 1634-1715. MS.L.s. to [John] Nelson; New York, 3 Dec 1683., (14); 1s.(2p.)
  Dongan, as governor of New York, disputes Nelson's right to grant land to settlers between the Kennebec and St. Croix Rivers.
- Dongan, Thomas, 2nd earl of Limerick, 1634-1715. MS.L.s. to [John] Nelson; New York, 6 Mar 1683-1684., (15); 1s.(2p.)
  Denying Nelson's rights, in greater detail than the preceding.
- Temple, John. MS.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 15 Aug 1687., (16); 1s.(2p.);
  also signed by Edmund Temple. A request for Nelson's aid in recovering £300 from Lady Hamilton, who was denying liability for the debt.
- Temple, Sir Peter. A.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 7 Mar 1688-1689., (17); 1s.(3p.)
  Thanking Nelson (his nephew) for gift of game and antlers.
- Temple, Sir Peter. A.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 10 Jan 1689-1690., (18); 1s.(2p.)
  Thanking Nelson for another gift of game and antlers, and urging his return to England so that his interests might best be looked after.
- Nelson, John, 1660-1721. Power of attorney in favor of James Lloyd. MS.(copy made ca.1824); Boston, 4 Aug 1691., (19); 1s.(2p.)
- Louis XIV, king of France, 1638-1715. MS.s.(contemporary copy); Versailles, 28 Jan 1693., (20); 1s.(1p.)
  Letter committing John Nelson to imprisonment in the Château d'Angoulême.
- Pontchartrain, Louis Phélypeaux, comte de, 1643-1727. MS.L.s.(contemporary copy) to the governor of the Château d'Angoulême; Versailles, 13 Jan 1694., (21); 1s.(2p.)
  Outlines the purposes and conditions of Nelson's bond and parole.
- Paschal, John. A.L.s. to [John] Nelson; London, 14 Jan 1694., (22); 1s.(2p.)
  Concerns the lack of progress in negotiations to effect the exchange of John Nelson with the French.
- Duport, M MS.(contemporary copy); La Rochelle, 12 Aug 1695., (23); 1s.(1p.)
  Duport engages to serve eighteen months in prison or pay 15,000 livres as bond for Nelson's return to France or successful execution of his mission of exchange.
- Louis XIV, king of France, 1638-1715. MS.s.; Versailles, 30 Nov 1695., (24); 1s.(1p.)
  Passport for John Nelson. Also signed by Louis Phélypeaux, Comte de Pontchartrain, and endorsed by the governor of the Château d'Angoulême.
- Wolselely, Robert, 1649-1697. MS.s.; Bruxelles, 21 Dec 1695., (25); 1s.(1p.)
  Passport to England for John Nelson, allowing Nelson fourteen days to effect passage.
- Kick, John. A.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 23 Jan 1695-1696., (26); 1s.(2p.)
  Blank space taken up with a draft in Nelson's hand of a letter setting forth his case, to an unnamed peer [Charles Talbot, Duke of Shrewsbury?]
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] A.L.(unsigned draft) to Charles Talbot, Duke of Shrewsbury; [London] Feb 1695-1696., (27); 1s.(2p.);
  imperfect. Draft of an appeal to Shrewsbury and the Lords of the Council.
- Randolph, Edward, 1640?-1700?. A.L.s. to [John] Nelson; [London] 29 Oct 1696., (28); 1s.(2p.)
  An offer to help Nelson obtain a hearing.
- Popple, William, d. 1708. MS.L.s. to [John] Nelson; Whitehall, 18 Nov 1696., (29); 1s.(1p.)
  Popple was Secretary of the Board of Trade. His four letters to Nelson all request information on the Nova Scotia claims and general situation in America.
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] A.MS.(unsigned copy); [London] 1 Dec 1696., (30); 1s.(4p.)
  Copie of my petition to his Majtie Decembr 1st 1696
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] The state and case of my affaires and circumstances with the French court... A.MS.(unsigned); [London?, Dec 1696?], (31); 2s.(8p.)
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] A.L.(unsigned draft) to [Charles Talbot, Duke of Shrewsbury?]; [London?, 1696?], (32); 4s.(16p.);
  possibly incomplete.
  Nelson's analysis of the position of the French in America, and his plea for British action.
- Mons, de la Fores petition for restitution of goods put on board ye Bonaventure c. MS.(unsigned); [n.p., c.1696], (33); 1s.(1p.)
  Concerns the recapture by the British of Fort York (Fort Bourbon) on Hudson's Bay.
- Popple, William, d. 1708. MS.L.s. to John Nelson; Whitehall, 24 Mar 1696-1697., (34); 1s.(2p.)
  See no. 29.
- Nelson, John, 1660-1721. A.L.s.(draft) to the Board of Trade; [London] 12 Apr 1697., (35); 1s.(4p.)
  A plea for relief in his difficulties with the French.
- Popple, William, d. 1708. MS.L.s. to John Nelson; Whitehall, 22 Jun 1697., (36); 1s.(2p.)
- Stamford, Thomas Gray, 2nd earl of, 1654-1720. MS.(notarial copy); [London] 1 Jul 1697., (37); 1s.(2p.)
  Copy of warrant for the arrest of John Nelson on the charge of high treason.
- Cobham, Sir Richard Temple, viscount, 1669?-1749. A.L.s. to [John] Nelson; [London, 23 Jul 1697.], (38); 1s.(2p.)
  Concerns his efforts in Nelson's behalf.
- Popple, William, d. 1708. MS.L.s. to John Nelson; Whitehall, 19 Oct 1697., (39); 1s.(2p.)
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] A.L.(unsigned draft) to the Board of Trade; [London, 1697?], (40); 1s.(4p.)
  Another plea for relief in his difficulties with the French.
- William III, king of Gt. Brit., 1650-1702. License for the return to England of Nelson from France. MS.s.(John Tench, depty to John Baron, Esq.); Westminster, 31 Jan 1698., (41); 1s.(1p.)
  On parchment. With 40s. tax stamp. Endorsed by Nelson on verso.
- Nelson, John, 1660-1721. To theire excellencies the Lds. Justices of Engld c.--- The humble ption of John Nelson... A.MS.(unsigned); [London?, 1698], (42); 1s.(2p.)
  Nelson's personal copy of his petition presenting his claim to Nova Scotia by inheritance.
- Paschal, John. A.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 15 Jan 1699., (43); 1s.(2p.)
  A report on the progress of Nelson's affairs before the Board of Trade.
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] A.L.(unsigned draft) to [Richard Coote, 1st earl of Bellamont, and James Vernon]; [London, 30 Sep 1699], (44); 2s.(7p.)
  Memorandum on Nova Scotian affairs, sent to Lord Bellamont as Governor of New England and Vernon as Principal Secretary of State.
- [Temple, Hester, lady, d. 1656] Record of my great grand-mother, ye Lady Temple. MS.(unsigned); Buckinghamshire [ca.1700?], (45); 1s.(1p.)
- [Nelson, John, 1660-1721] The treaty made and concluded by Col. Phillips,; Col. Townsend,; Capt. Byfield my selfe wth the Easterne Indians... MS.(unsigned, contempory copy); Casco Bay, 3 Jun 1701., (46); 2s.(6p.)
  Confirming the Albany treaty of 1701, and adding provisions.
- Vaudreuil, Philippe de Rigaud, marquis de, 1640-1725. MS.L.s. to [John] Nelson; Quebec, 12 Feb 1713., (47); 1s.(3p.)
- Tailer, William. A.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 3 Apr 1717., (48); 1s.(2p.)
  About the progress of Nelson's Nova Scotian claims.
- Cobham, Sir Richard Temple, viscount, 1669?-1749. MS.L.(copy) to [Col. ] Taylor; London, 18 Aug 1719., (49); 1s.(2p.)
  Includes letter to Taylor from Sir Francis Nicholson, both letters dealing with Temple-Nelson claims. With this is 2nd MS. copy of same pair of letters.
- Nicholson, Sir Francis, 1655-1728. MS.L.s. to Thomas Nelson; London, 31 Mar 1720., (50); 1s.(4p.)
- Vaudreuil, Philippe de Rigaud, marquis de, 1640-1725. MS.L.s. to [John] Nelson; Montreal, 4 Aug 1724., (51); 1s.(3p.)
- Vaudreuil, Philippe de Rigaud, marquis de, 1640-1725. MS.L.s. to [John] Nelson; Quebec, 16 Oct 1724., (52); 1s.(3p.)
  Concerning the surprise attack on Norridgewock and related matters.
- [Nelson, John, d. 1734] A.L.(unsigned draft) to [Philippe de Rigaud, marquis de Vaudreuil]; Boston, 12 Jan 1724-1725., (53); 1s.(4p.)
  Concerns the ransoming of a Mr. Edgar from the Indians, merits of British and French claims in North America, and other matters.
- Nelson, Paschal. [Extract made by Paschal Nelson, ca.1750 from the preceding letter and intended to support his claims to Nova Scotian property], (54); 1s.(2p.)
  This John Nelson was son of John Nelson ( 1660-1721 ).
- Vaudreuil, Philippe de Rigaud, marquis de, 1640-1725. MS.L.s. to [John Nelson]; Montreal, 2 May 1725., (55); 3s.(9p.)
  A reply to Nelson's letter of 12 Jan (no. 53).
- Cobham, Sir Richard Temple, viscount, 1669?-1749. A.L.s. to John Nelson; London, 14 Oct 16?6., (56); 1s.(2p.)
  Reports Cobham's unsuccessful efforts to obtain preferment for (presumably) Paschal Nelson.
- Nelson, John, 1734. [Last will and testament] MS.(copy made ca.1824); probated Boston, 23 Dec 1734., (57); 2s.(3p.)
  The paper upon which this copy is written is watermarked 1824.
- Joncaire, [] A.L.s. to []; "aux Jonontotians", 15 Jan 1740., (58); 1s.(3p.)
  A letter carried by Indian runners; concerning the robbery of a certain Sieur Fleurdépée, and various business matters.
- Cobham, Sir Richard Temple, viscount, 1669?-1749. MS.L.(copy by Paschal Nelson?) to Sir William Yonge; [London] 3 May 1744., (59); 1s.(1p.)
  Supporting Paschal Nelson's claims.
- Nelson, Paschal, b.ca.1710. The memorial of Paschal Nelson. MS.(unsigned); [London?, ca.1750?], (60); 3s.(8p.)
  Setting forth claims (through Sir Thomas Temple and the elder John Nelson) for reimbursement by the government for loss of property in Nova Scotia.
- [Temple, Sir Thomas, bart., 1614-1674] Abstract of Sr Tho. Temples affairs Tittle to Nova Scotia. MS.(unsigned); [n.p.,ca.1750], (61); 1s.(2p.)
  An outline of facts presented in Paschal Nelson's memorial. Rough draft of proposed appeal for franchise to clothe the S.C. regiment to which P.N. belonged.
- State of the English right to Nova Scotia. MS.(unsigned); [n.p., ca.1750?], (62); 1s.(2p.)
  Part of the same series of documents as the preceding, evidently compiled in support of Paschal Nelson's claim.
- [Nelson, Paschal, b.ca.1710] [Memorandum on the New York militia, etc.] A.MS.(unsigned draft?); [n.p.,ca.1750?], (63); 1s.(1p.)
- Temple, Robert. A.L.s. to his "dr brother"; Ten Hills, 26 Dec 1753., (64); 1s.(3p.)
  Concerns the attempt to locate certain papers dealing with the Nova Scotia claims; also a quarrel about riparian rights between the Kennebec proprietors and the Massachusetts Bay Colony.
- Nelson, Paschal, b.ca.1710. A.L.(unsigned draft) to [George Montagu Dunk, 2nd earl of Halifax?]; [London?, ca.1754?], (65); 1s.(3p.)
- [Nelson, Paschal, b.ca.1710.] Represent[ation] conc[erning] Georgia. A.MS.(unsigned); [London?, ca.1754], (66); 1s.(3p.)
  Plans for the improvement of Georgia, drawn up and submitted in support of an application for its governorship.
- [Nelson, Paschal, b.ca.1710] A.L.(unsigned draft) to [George Montagu Dunk, 2nd earl of Halifax]; [London?, 1754], (67); 1s.(3p.)
  Thanking Halifax for his efforts in behalf of Nelson's unsuccessful application for the governorship of Georgia.
- [Memorandum concerning French encrochments in America and the need for a union of British colonies there] MS.(unsigned); [n.p., ca.1755], (68); 1s.(4p.)
  Although not in his autograph, this may be by Paschal Nelson. It is dated from its reference to the building of the French fort at Ticonderoga, in 1751.
- [Nelson, Paschal, b.ca.1710.] [Memorandum on a] perpetual barrier between the English and Canada. A.MS.(unsigned draft); [n.p., ca.1755], (69); 1s.(1p.)
  Plan for a line of forts and blockhouses to cut the French off from the British colonies.
- Lloyd, James, 1728-1810. A.L.s. to John Nelson; Boston, 25 Jan 1768., (70); 1s.(3p.)
  A letter of advice to Nelson, who was in Dominica attempting to recover some money owed to Lloyd and others.
- Nelson family. [Family records, memoranda, etc., mostly relating to John Nelson; various dates, mostly 19th century], (71); 5 pieces.